In addition to inheritance
(i.e., the kind of generalization/specialization
we've looked at so far), there are
other, further relationships between classes in UML.
Ultimately, these are then relationships that
are also reflected at the object level
We will look at the
following three types of relationships here.
These are by no means
all that are present in UML.
So there's still
dependency, usage relationships, genericity,
parameterization.
But those are the three
that we're going to look at.
While inheritance is explicitly seen
only in class diagrams (while in
the object diagram inheritance no
longer exists as a drawn connection
somehow), association, aggregation, composition
will actually be explicitly
represented in both class
diagrams and associated object diagrams.
These three types of relationships are
different in strength, so to speak.
So ultimately, association is the weakest
form of these three types of connections.
Aggregation is in a
certain sense a special association.
And composition as the
strongest kind of relation
here is again
a more special aggregation.
That's why it makes sense that we look
at these three types of relationships in order.
And in fact, in this
video, I'm just going to talk
about association and related
modeling aspects for now.
In particular, also about annotations that you can
still add to diagrams when you have associations.
And later, in a separate video,
we will talk about aggregation and composition.
Where some of the aspects of association
continue to occur, but more are added.
So we'll start with
the weakest relationship, association.
It's actually so weak
that it's very broadly defined.
So you talk about
an association between two classes.
It's always about two classes:
abstractly now class A, class B.
And they are associated (or: there is
an association between them), if there is
somehow a semantic connection between these
classes, which one can name meaningfully.
So if you
can't think of a
meaningful name, then there's no
content relation between these classes.
And this relation, this
connection, is not hierarchical.
So first of all a rather
vague concept, as it is written here.
This "not hierarchical" aspect is
relevant, because if anything is hierarchical,
then it is most likely either
an inheritance (so hierarchical in the
sense of belonging; in
the sense of specialization/generalization;
belonging of objects of one
class also to the other class),
or it will be aggregation or
composition (in the sense of hierarchical
part-whole relationships, but as I
said, this will concern us later).
So
ultimately:
Association, still very general, simply expresses
that objects of one class (perhaps A)
need a connection to certain
objects of the other class
for their functionality (at least for
some part of what they exist for).
So A objects are supposed to
do something that B objects are also
useful for, or perhaps can
be called upon to help with.
And if that is sufficiently important for
the relationship, the connection to exist, that it
should be stored persistently (i.e. not
fleetingly relevant only briefly in the
course of the system,
but actually a persistent/permanently
stored connection should exist
between these objects), then
it makes sense to
express that by an association.
And actually in
an implementation of an
object-oriented system such a connection
would be made by the
fact that for example objects of the one
class refer to objects of the other class.
So usually by one of
the classes having an attribute
whose type is
the other class.
Then objects of the
other class can be accessed.
Suppose there is an attribute in class A
whose type is class B, then yes, in every
object of class A there is something stored that
refers to a B. This will be the case.
However, it will be the case
(that's why this is emphasized again)
that this special type of attributes will just
then no longer be entered into the classes.
Because you have another graphical
means for the associations, which is
more memorable than always
writing attributes in there.
We will not
enter these so-called reference
attributes explicitly in
the class diagram.
Instead, we will have
a graphical means, simply
an edge in the graph,
which is representative for it:
That's this kind of relationship
that you can implement through attributes.
How is
that meant?
So instead of A and
B, let's do something more concrete.
Let one class be
a class of people.
Let the other class
be a class of cars.
And persons
can own cars.
And instead of entering "mycar"
in the attribute list for "person"
(as attribute, which then
has "car" as type),
you simply insert a graphical
connection between these two classes.
And then assign a meaningful
name, namely: it is about property.
So a person owns
a car, for example.
Whereby here is
not yet somehow specified
that each person has exactly one car
or always only one person owns a car.
As the relationship stands here,
it is deliberately not to be
excluded that a person can also
have several cars or own no car.
Or that a car can
be owned by several persons together.
The point here is only that this kind
of relationship between people and cars exists at all.
For that to happen, at least one side
would have to have a reference to the other.
For example, in the implementation, as
already indicated, there could be an attribute
at Person that stores a
car or even several cars.
But one does not enter this,
but uses this kind of representation to
make the
connection clear.
Because of this fact that here it
is not required that each car belongs to
only one person (each person owns
exactly one car), different expressions of this
relation are quite conceivable on
the level of concrete objects.
So it could be that there are
exactly three persons and three cars and exactly
person 1 is related to car 1, person
2 to car 2, person 3 to car 3.
That would be possible,
but it is not obligatory.
It could also be, for example,
that there are these three persons, but:
Person 1 owns both car 1 and car
2, and person 2 does not own any cars
at all and therefore does not appear in
this listing here, and person 3 owns car 3.
That would
be conceivable.
Or here
is another constellation:
Person 1 owns cars 1 and 2, person 2 owns
car 2, and person 3 may not exist at all.
Or there are still quite a few persons,
but they do not own any other cars.
What is not covered here,
however, and also not wanted:
For example, person 1
owns car 1 multiple times.
Person 1 can own several cars, but
it makes no sense to write down here:
Person 1, Car 1, and
then again Person 1, Car 1.
Why
is that?
Because these are quantities,
related to your math lecture.
Or in the case
of the Komedia students:
Referring to my math lecture
from last semester, these are relations.
Sets of pairs, or subsets of the
cross product of the set of all
people and the set of all cars
(which are reasonable interpretations of these classes).
Then these
are relations here.
That is,
one asks:
Does person 1
own car 1?
Yes
or no?
And
not:
Person 1 owns car 1, and
person 1 owns car 1 again.
That's why the set
representation makes sense here.
By the way, what I actually
wanted to say in the last example:
The point here was exactly that this is an
example where car 2 is owned by two people.
That was the point
in the last example here,
because there's no data here that
would restrict that in any way.
That can also be restricted,
we will also see shortly.
Then you would add numbers
to the ends of this association.
But in this case,
there is no further restriction.
Therefore, all these three and
many more forms are conceivable.
Now I
had said:
Person
owns car.
That seems to fit by chance,
because when I read it that way,
"Person owns car", it corresponds
exactly to a German sentence.
That is,
of course, coincidental.
I could also
have accidentally recorded the
two classes exactly
reversed in my graph.
That's why
it can be
important to actually give some direction
on this name for this association.
So who actually
owns who here?
This can be done by this black
triangular arrow at the name of the association.
So that is to be
seen as the reading direction:
"person
owns car".
If I wanted cars to own people,
I could still draw it that way,
but would just have this triangular
arrow pointing here (towards the person).
This is simply a
reading direction of the association.
Besides that, there is
the so-called navigation direction.
This is expressed by an arrow, and
this very special kind of arrow (clearly distinguishable
from the inheritance arrow), added
directly to the association line.
This expresses
the navigation direction.
And this describes, objects
of which class must
know their association partners and
therefore can call their methods.
This means
for example:
In the example
earlier I said it
could be that Person has an
attribute where a car is stored.
Then the person
can access the car.
Then that would correspond
to that navigation direction.
So for example, the
person knows their cars
because they have them
stored in an attribute.
If that would be as specified here, it would
mean the other way around (because there is no arrow
specified here in the other direction) that
the cars themselves do not know their owners.
So if modeled
as here, it
would mean that there is no
attribute with type Person in the car.
In a sense, these
navigation directions are a hint,
or an anticipation,
of the implementation.
There may also be no
navigation direction specified at all.
Then it is usually assumed that this
is either simply not important in the
current modeling state, or that the
association is navigable in both directions.
In the example as it is given here,
the idea would be, as just said, that it
is the Person objects that have references
to Auto objects, and not vice versa.
Since it should still be allowed that a
person can own several cars, it is of
course not enough to
store exactly one car here.
For each person, a set
of cars owned by that
person would have
to be stored.
For example it could be that for person 1
the set \ is stored,
for person 2 the empty set, and for
person 3 the set \.
That would then correspond to
this second mapping, this relation.
If we don't store this
as pairs, but for each
person simply store the
set of corresponding cars.
Person 1: car
1 and car 2.
Person 2
has no cars.
And person 3
has car 3.
We would then store that in
the three concrete person objects respectively.
In principle, the reading direction
and the navigation direction can differ.
So we model the person-owns-car
relationship, but still we don't
store cars with the person, but vice
versa with the cars with the persons.
This is somewhat unusual, and
in fact one would probably assume
that we have
not modeled well here.
So if reading
direction and navigation direction
are different, then maybe
this relationship is just misnamed.
If it really is the cars that remember which
persons they belong to, then instead of "owns" it should
say "belongs to" here, and the reading
direction should be in the other direction.
"Car belongs to person"
instead of "person owns car".
Conversely, if you just have the association
navigable in both directions, then the reading
direction is relevant mainly for understanding,
for the intention of the model.
While the implementation doesn't
care, because each person remembers
the cars anyway and the cars
also remember which person they belong to.
Then one decided to call this
association nevertheless "owns" and not "belongs".
And then one indicates just by this arrow,
in which direction here the possession is present.
If no navigation directions
are given at all, it's
either that maybe it's not
important at the time you're modeling.
Or there
are conventions.
For example, people on the team (the team
that is modeling together) have agreed and specified:
If no navigation directions are drawn,
then both should always be present.
I'm not going to
define that further here.
Those were these different kinds of
arrows that you can have in associations.
Then I mentioned earlier that you
can also have numbers at the associations.
These are
the so-called multiplicities.
And they are intervals in the
general case, so somehow two numbers.
As "from"/"to" this
is to be read.
There is also the special case
that there is only one number.
Then from this number
to this number is meant.
So it is not a real interval, but
only exactly one number, which comes into question.
It could look like this
(let's forget the navigation directions again,
they should not
be relevant right now):
We have the association,
we have a name, we
have a reading direction, and we
have multiplicities here in each case.
How is this
to be read?
As follows. This specification
at this end means:
Each person has
0 to 5 cars.
So there are between 0 and
5 cars associated with every single person.
And the 1
at this end means:
Each car belongs
to exactly one person.
So you have to remember
how around that is meant.
The 1
does not mean:
Every person
has a car.
But each car
belongs to one person.
And each person owns
up to five cars.
That means, here you can also see, that if the
persons should have an attribute with type car, this would
have to be a quantity attribute (because
up to five cars have to be stored).
So now
in programming language:
Depending on what you have already heard
in lectures and listen to in parallel,
you may have learned about
lists, sets, arrays as collections.
So here, one such collection would
have to be stored for each person
in order to be able
to remember up to five cars.
Conversely, if this association were to
be navigable in the other direction,
each car would need
to remember only one person.
So you wouldn't need a collection in that
direction, but you would need one in that direction.
Now you could
play around a bit.
You could make a 1
into a 2, for example.
What does
that mean here?
You have to
visualize it again:
What does
it mean?
It doesn't mean that two people always
own up to five cars exactly together.
That is not how
it is to be read.
What is to
be read is:
Each person owns up to five cars, and
each car is owned by exactly two people.
But it need not always be the
same consistent pairs of people for different cars.
So it would be quite possible that
person 1 owns cars 1 and 2,
person 2 also owns car 1, but car
2 has as second owner a person 3.
Then the
following applies here:
Each person has
up to five cars.
Person 1
has two cars.
Person 2
has one car.
Person 3
And each car belongs
to exactly two persons.
Car 1 belongs to
person 1 and person 2.
Car 2 belongs to
person 1 and person 3.
But no car belongs to
exactly the same two people.
Again, you just have
to read it this way:
Each person has
up to five cars.
Each car belongs
to exactly two people.
But this can be mixed, so to speak,
who are the owners of two different cars each.
It would also be conceivable that there
are other people, but no other cars.
Because each person must
own up to five cars,
but that can be zero
cars for a given person.
What is not possible here,
of course, is that there are
more cars but
no more people.
Each additional car would have
to have at least two owners.
So it would be possible that
there are cars 3, 4 and
5, which all
belong to person 1.
But then they would also have
to be named in this set.
Generally there will be
such intervals at both ends.
So abstractly for names of classes A and B and respectively
their interval m to n, k to l, this would mean
that between m and n instances of A
can be associated to an instance of B.
So I take an instance of
class B, then i, between m
and n, can have
A instances as partners.
And vice versa, if you
have an instance of A,
then there must be j instances of B associated
with it, where j must lie between k and l.
The examples just now
were simply manifestations of this.
If you don't want to have an upper bound here
(i.e. you don't want to say "from m to n",
but always just "at least m"), then
you can write an asterisk for it.
This stands
for "infinite".
So if you want to
say "there must be at least
two, but there can be any
number", you write "2 to star".
Conversely, if one would have wanted to say,
"at most two", one would have written: "0..2".
The lower bound is
of course zero and for
the upper bound one inserts a
star as a sign for "infinite".
What if there
is nothing at all?
We also had the case,
before we introduced multiplicities, that
there is
nothing at all.
Then it is again
a matter of convention.
UML itself does not
specify a standard multiplicity.
In some books it says,
agreed as standard multiplicity, 1.
But UML itself
does not specify one.
For diagrams in the
lecture, in the exercise, also
in the exam, it will be the
case that if there is no specification, the
multiplicity "0..*" is taken as the
default, so simply no restriction at all.
Anything from zero to
any number could be possible.
This is true for associations, partly also
for aggregation, but not anymore for composition.
We'll get
to that later.
So
basically:
Association and Aggregation
use this convention.
Composition uses a different convention, which
we'll talk about in the corresponding video.
Before that, one more
way of representing associations.
Sometimes, instead of giving the connecting line a
name (like the "owns" just now), you give the
two ends of the
connecting line a name instead.
This is useful when, for
example, there are clearly distributed roles
taken by the two
ends of such an association.
Then it may be unnecessary
to name the association itself.
In the case of "owns", the two
roles could have been named "owner" and "possessed".
Then there would have been no need to
say that the relationship is one of possession.
Or here's
another example:
There are wholesalers, there are individual
retailers, and there are end customers.
In each case, relationships
in between, that is, associations.
In each of these
associations, there is a part
that has a seller role, and
a part that has a buyer role.
Between wholesaler and retailer, the wholesaler is
the seller and the retailer is the buyer.
Whereas between retailer and end customer, the retailer is
the seller and the end customer is the buyer.
So the retailer
participates in two associations
with different partners
in different roles.
And then just the association is
not named anymore, because the two roles,
which are at the ends, already
convey enough information about this association.
That much about associations.